Inventory of the Thomas Roderick Dew Papers ca. 1830-1967
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Thomas Roderick Dew Papers, ca. 1830-1967.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Archives Acc. 1980.122
71 items.
Papers of and relating to Thomas Roderick Dew, professor of political law and president of the College of William and Mary.
Thomas Roderick Dew.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Biographical Information
Thomas R. Dew was born 5 December 1802, the son of Thomas Dew and Lucy E. Gatewood Dew. Dew graduated from the College of William and Mary in 1820. He was appointed to teach political law in 1826 and in 1836 was made president of the college. He died in 1846, shortly after his marriage to Natilia Hay. A free-trader and a pro-slavery advocate, Dew's works included Lectures on the Restrictive System, Review of the Debate [on the abolition of slavery] in the Virginia Legislature of 1831-'32 (later incorporated into the Pro-Slavery Argument), and Digest of the Laws, Customs, Manners, and Institutions of the Ancient and Modern Nations.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, ca. 1830-1967, or and relating to Thomas Roderick Dew, professor of political law and president of the College of William and Mary. Includes biographical material, a picture of a portrait, correspondence, speeches and writings, as well as information on his gravesite in Paris and his reburial in the Wren Chapel.
Related material
The University Archives owns a number of notebooks kept by students attending Dew's lectures.
Index Terms
Persons:
Dew, Thomas Roderick, 1802- 1846.
Family Names:
Dew family.
Corporate Names:
College of William and Mary--History--19th century.
Contents List
- Biographical material., 23 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
  Articles, notes, and excerpts from various sources.
- Picture., 3 items. (Box-folder 1:2)
  Photocopies and notes on the portrait of Thomas Dew owned by William & Mary.
- Autograph., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:3)
  Inside back cover of an unidentified book with inscription: "Presented to W. S. Peachy by his friend, Thos. R. Dew, prof. Wm & Mary College".
- Correspondence., 8 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Thomas R. Dew, William & Mary College, to Governor W. B. Giles, 22 February 1830., 1 page. ALS.
    Letter of introduction for Col. C. de la Pena, professor of modern languages at William & Mary.
  - Transcriptions, 1835-1836., 3 items.
    Transcriptions of three letters not owned by the College of William and Mary.
  - Thomas R. Dew, Dewsville near New Town, King & Queen, Virginia, to Prof. J. Millington, Philadelphia, 7 September 1836., 2 pages. ALS.
    Lists the books Dew has recently purchased for the college library.
  - T. R. Dew, William & Mary College, to William H. Harrison (Principal of the Academy at the Wigwam), Elkhill, Amelia, 18 October 1838., 3 pages. Photocopy of ALS.
    Draft of letter replying to Harrison's letter of October 8 in which Harrison complemented Dew's publications. Discusses availability of his publications on economy and history. Dew is "glad to find that you agree with me on the subject of slavery. Every day convinces me of its blessings in southern latitudes. I think you are right in regard to Liberia - Man cannot be uplifted from barbarism to civilization without the aid of slavery - All history demonstrates this proposition." College has opened with bright prospects, nearly 100 in attendance. Students from Harrison's seminary have always been among the most successful at the college. Includes drafts of orders to Messrs. Smith & Palmer, Richmond, to deliver a copy of Dew's lectures on the Restrictive System to Harrison; and to Edmund Ruffin, Petersburg, to deliver a copy of Dew's Historical Notes to Harrison.
  - Corrections., 2 pages. AN.
    Corrections for a publication and additional footnotes to be inserted, on public speeches in France, England, and America, and on Mr. Randolph's process of composing speeches.
    On same leaf as end of a letter draft, signed, dated 1 June 1841.
  - T. R. Dew, 13 March 1846., 2 pages. ADS.
    Praises conditions and new buildings at Eastern Asylum of Virginia under Dr. Galt.
- Addresses and writings., 7 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Communication of Wm. Harper and Thomas R. Dew, in relation to the memorial of the Committee of the Free Trade Convention against the Tariff, 13 February, 1832.
    Doc. No. 82, House of Representatives, 22d Congress, 1st Session.
  - Thomas R. Dew, Review of the Debate [on the abolition of slavery] in the Virginia Legislature, 1831-'32, The Political Register, vol. II (Washington: 16 October 1833)., 2 copies.
  - Bibliographic notes.
    Compiled by E. G. Swem.
- Addresses and writings., 9 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Thomas R. Dew, Essay on the Interest of Money, and the Policy of Laws against Usury(Shellbanks, Va.: 1834).
  - T. R. Dew, handwritten communication to the Board of Visitors of the College of William & Mary, 3 July 1836., 30 pages. ADS.
    Gives his detailed arguments in favor of his existing arrangements of the course structure and fees for classes in history.
  - Thomas R. Dew, An Address on the Influence of the Federative Republican System of Government upon Literature and the Development of Character, Prepared to be Delivered before the Historical and Philosophical Society of Virginia at their Annual Meeting in 1836(Richmond: Southern Literary Messenger, 1836).
  - Southern Literary Messenger, March 1940.
    Reprint of Dew's 1836 address.
  - Bibliographical notes.
  - The Great Question of the Day: Letter from President Thomas R. Dew of William and Mary College, Virginia, to a Representative in Congress from that State; on the Subject of the Financial Policy of the Administration and the Laws of Credit and Trade(Washington: 1840)., Photocopy.
- Burial., 16 items. (Box-folder 1:7)
  Photographs, photocopies of photographs, programs, and other information concerning Dew's grave in France and the memorial service and reburial of his remains in Williamsburg in 1939.
- Family information., 4 items. (Box-folder 1:8)
  Published biographical information on William Dunbar Evans, John Garnett Dew, Benjamin Franklin Dew, James Harvie Dew; and a coat of arms entitled Dew family, by an unknown artist.